The Strait of Hormuz is the Gulf's
narrow gate to the Arabian Sea.
It sits between Iran to the north,
and Oman and the UAE to the south.
Around one fifth of the world's oil
and liquefied natural gas usually
passes through this corridor.
That makes Hormuz a chokepoint: when
war approaches these waters,
shipping risk jumps and prices
follow.
After the attacks on 28 February,
Iran effectively blocked the strait.
That turned Hormuz into a pressure
point for tankers, insurers, and
governments.
When Iran and the United States
agreed to a ceasefire tied to safe
passage, markets exhaled.
Oil prices fell by about fifteen
percent, proving how a small strait
can shake the global economy.