Before Transformers, sequence models
read text one token at a time, so
long-range links were slow and
fragile.
Self-attention changed that: every
token can look directly at every
other token in the sequence.
Each token starts as an embedding
plus a positional encoding, so the
model knows meaning and order.
From that matrix X, it learns
queries, keys, and values.
Queries seek, keys match, and values
carry the information forward.
The core step is QK transpose over
root d-k, then softmax, then
a weighted mix of V.
Those weights make meaning
contextual, and multi-head attention
lets different heads track different
relationships at once.
Stacked blocks train in parallel,
but attention still has a quadratic
cost.