The Strait of Hormuz is a narrow sea
gate between Iran, Oman, and the
United Arab Emirates.
It links the Gulf to the Arabian
Sea, and one fifth of global oil and
LNG passes through.
That makes the strait a chokepoint:
peaceful in calm times, but brutally
exposed when war closes in.
After U.S. and Israeli attacks on
Iran on 28 February, Tehran
effectively blocked the route.
A local military crisis suddenly
became a global shipping and energy
crisis.
Then a ceasefire tied to safe
passage reopened confidence, and oil
prices fell by about fifteen
percent.
For tanker crews and insurers,
Hormuz means daily risk: missiles,
drones, insurance costs, and delay.
That is why a waterway only thirty
three kilometers wide can still
shake the world economy.